# Pengyu Cheng □ pengyu.cheng@duke.edu • • linear95.github.io

## **Research Interests**

I am a fourth-year Ph.D. candidate in the Department of Electric and Computer Engineering at Duke University. My research interests focus on probabilistic machine learning, interpretable machine learning, and their applications in natural language processing.

## Education

Duke University 08/2017 – Present

Ph.D. Student, Electrical and Computer Engineering

Tsinghua University 08/2013 – 07/2017

B.S., Mathematics and Statistics

## Experience

#### Information Initiative at Duke (iiD)

08/2017 - Present

Research Assistant Adviser: Lawrence Carin

Bayesian deep learning, geometric deep learning, and their applications in natural language processing.

**Microsoft Cloud and AI** 06/2020 – 08/2020

Research Internship Mentor: Jingjing Liu

Improving self-supervised multi-view contrastive learning with learnable data augmentations.

**NEC Laboratories America** 05/2019 – 08/2019

Research Internship Mentor: Martin Rengiang Min

Improving disentangled text representation learning with information-theoretic guidance.

## Tsinghua Intelligent Vision Group (IVG)

03/2016 - 07/2016

Student Researcher Adviser: Jiwen Lu

Deep metric learning for person re-identification based on sequential frames information.

#### Student Research Program at Tsinghua

11/2015 - 05/2017

Student Researcher Adviser: Xuegong Zhang

Non-parametric k-sample tests with statistics based on local maximum energy distance.

#### Sogou Map Rendering Group

08/2014 - 09/2014

Research Internship Mentor: Mao Wang

Automatic smoothing and compression for polygonal line-like city road data.

## **Selected Publications**

- o **P. Cheng**\*, W. Hao\*, S. Yuan, S. Si, L. Carin, "FairFil: Contrastive Neural Debiasing Method for Pretrained Text Encoders", International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2021
- S. Yuan\*, P. Cheng\*, R. Zhang, W. Hao, Z. Gan, and L. Carin, "Improving Zero-Shot Voice Style Transfer via Disentangled Representation Learning", International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2021
- P. Cheng, W. Hao, S. Dai, J. Liu, Z. Gan, and L. Carin, "CLUB: A Contrastive Log-ratio Upper Bound of Mutual Information", International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2020

- P. Cheng, M. Min, D. Shen, C. Malon, Y. Zhang, Y. Li and L. Carin, "Improving Disentangled Text Representation Learning with Information-Theoretic Guidance", Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), 2020
- P. Cheng, Y. Li, X. Zhang, L. Chen, D. Carlson, L. Carin, "Dynamic Embedding on Textual Networks via a Gaussian Process", American Association of Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2020 Oral
- P. Cheng\*, D. Shen\*, D. Sundararaman, X. Zhang, Q. Yang, M. Tang, A. Celikyilmaz, and L. Carin, "Learning Compressed Sentence Representations for On-Device Text Processing", Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), 2019 Oral
- o **P. Cheng**, C. Liu, C. Li, D. Shen, H. Ricardo, and L. Carin, "Straight-Through Estimator as Projected Wasserstein Gradient Flow", Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) Workshop, 2018 Spotlight

## **Technical Reviewer**

Conference: AAAI 2020; NeurIPS 2020; ICML 2020; AAAI 2021; ICLR 2021; IJCAI 2021

Journal: IEEE Trans. Signal Process 2020

## **Academic Activities**

o Oral Presentation at AAAI 2020	02/2020
o Teaching assistant for <i>Probabilistic Machine Learning</i> , Instructor: Sayan Mukherjee, Ph.D.	01/2020
o Teaching assistant for <i>Introduction to Deep Learning</i> , Instructor: Vahid Tarokh, Ph.D.	09/2019
o Oral Presentation at ACL 2019	07/2019
o Spotlight talk at NeurIPS 2019 Bayesian Deep Learning workshop	12/2018

## **Awards**

o Fellowship of Electrical and Computer Engineering at Duke	08/2017
o First in Duke-Tsinghua Machine Learning Summer School (1/112)	08/2017
o Academic Excellence Award of Tsinghua University (top 30%)	10/2014
o Top 5 in the 18-th "Sogou Cup" Artificial Intelligence Programming Contest (5/200)	04/2014
o Silver medal in the 28-th Chinese Mathematical Olympiad (CMO)	01/2013
o First Prize in Chinese National Olympiad in Informatics in Provinces (NOIP)	11/2012

## **Technical Strengths**

**Computer Languages**: Python (Tensorflow, Pytorch), R, C/C++

Software & Tools: LaTeX, Emacs, Mathematica, MATLAB, Excel, Markdown

### **Graduate Courses**

**Theoretical**: Random Signals and Noise; Information Theory; Multivariate Statistical Analysis; Stochastic Processes; Compressed Sensing;

**Engineering**: Programming, Data Structure and Algorithms in C++; Pattern Recognition; Machine Learning; Text Data Analysis; Scalable Reinforcement Learning;